Guide to the Edwin B. Morgan papers, 1840-1888.
Morgan, Edwin B. papers, 1840-1888.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Edwin B. Morgan papers, 1840-1888.
550
Edwin Barber Morgan.
.4 cubic ft.
Correspondence, tallies, votes, minutes, news clippings, broadsides, and other papers.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Papers concerned principally with elections in the 25th Congressional District of New York (Cayuga County) in 1850; Morgan's platform included high protectionism, free soil, and the repeal of the Fugitive Slave Law; he was defeated by Thomas Y. How, the Loco-Foco candidate.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Whig Congressman, elected in 1852.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Papers concerned principally with elections in the 25th Congressional District of New York (Cayuga County) in 1850; Morgan's platform included high protectionism, free soil, and the repeal of the Fugitive Slave Law; he was defeated by Thomas Y. How, the Loco-Foco candidate. Includes material on the Whig nominating convention in Homer, details of the campaign, and Morgan's defeat. Also, material relating to Cornell University and to Wells College and Aurora, New York; later papers deal with state and national politics and the 1852 elections. Also includes letters from Horace Greeley, William Seward, Ezra Cornell, Edward Selkreg, Joseph Esty, Henry Morghan, and local politicians.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Morgan, Edwin Barber.; Cornell, Ezra, 1807-1874.; Esty, Joseph.; Greeley, Horace, 1811-1872.; How, Thomas Y.; Morgan, Henry.; Selkreg, Edward.; Seward, William Henry, 1801-1872.; Wells, Henry.; Cornell University--Students.; Free Soil Party (N.Y.); United States.; Wells College.; Whig Party (N.Y.)
Subjects:
Protectionism--United States.; Politics, Practical--New York (State); Congressmen.
Places:
Cayuga County (N.Y.)--Politics and government.; Aurora (N.Y.)--History.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- Correspondence (1849-1854), 120 pieces
  - Letters between E.B. Morgan, Whig candidate for Congress in 1850, and party members including Washington Hunt, General Scott, R.H. Duell and others prominent in both state and national politics, and his brother Christopher Morgan, himself a former Representative. A few letters concerning Morgan's successful fight for election in 1852. (Box 1, Folder A)
    Interesting letters:
    Oct. 16, 1850, Horace Greeley to Morgan. "I feel sure we shall beat this time.... You must help us for land reform in Congress.... I have nothing else to ask."
    Oct. 26, 1850, Morgan to a committee composed of Hiram Plumb, James Lester, Nathaniel Vilas, William Kevill, setting forth stand on Fugitive Slave Law - "one of the most cruel and wicked laws ever enacted by a legislative body" - and free soil: "I am decidedly in favor of extending that ordinance [of 1787] over the territories - believing it to be the only safe mode of excluding slavery."
    Nov. 7, 1850, William Henry Seward to Morgan, "Our friends still cluster in the Advertiser office and occupy themselves with conjectures to reduce the majorities reported for your adversary and enhance your own."
    Nov. 7, 1850 (same date as above), Seward to Morgan. "Our generous and faithful friends resisted the evidences of your defeat to day until the authentic reports from Cortland rendered hope no longer possible."
    Nov. 9, 1850, R.H. Duell, of Cortland Village, to Morgan explaining Morgan's defeat in those places where he was behind. Tells of the concentration of the locofocos against him and of the treachery of the Auburn Whigs who helped to defeat him despite the general Whig Victory.
    Apr. 9, 1851, Morgan to Governor Washington Hunt concerning a fugitive slave from Maryland.
    Jan. 31, 1852, Morgan to Winfield Scott pledging the former's support of the latter should he be nominated for the presidency.
- Whig Party material
  - Tallies, votes, conference minutes, lists of prominent Whigs, party notices, etc. (Box 1, Folder B)
  - Newspaper clippings concerning elections. (Box 1, Folder B)
- Broadsides
  To view these items, request Mapcase Folders 38-39 from collection #6629 - Regional history broadsides
  - Advertisement (Store). Circular: Dry Goods, Groceries, Crockery, etc. Charles C. Dilts, Livonia, N.Y. Oct. 1852. (Mapcase-folder 38)
    To view this item, request from collection #6629 - Regional history broadsides
  - Political. Cortland County Whig Extra, Homer, N.Y., Thursday, Oct. 31, 1850. The Whit Candidate for Member of Assembly! His views in regard to United States Senator, etc. (Alvan Kellogg). (Mapcase-folder 38)
  - Political. Cayuga New Era Extra, Auburn, N.Y., Nov. 2 [1850?] Democrats Organize! White Candidate for Congress [E.B. Morgan] in desperation. (Mapcase-folder 38)
  - Political. Democratic Voters of Cayuga: Down with Thomas Y. How and the Rathbun family! Down with the Thimble Riggers of Genesee Street! (Mapcase-folder 39)
  - Political. General Scott's Illegal and Unjust Demands upon the Public Treasury! His Receipt of Public Money Against the Law! Read, Farmer, Mechanic Labourer! Read All! Read Carefully! [1852?] (Mapcase-folder 39)
  - Political (Edwin B. Morgan vs. Locofocos). Sworn affadavit that Colonel Edwin B. Morgan, Whit Candidate for Congress is no longer owner of a travern in Auburn, N.Y. Oct. 29, 1852. (8 cop.) (Mapcase-folder 39)
  - Political. Circular to the Whigs of the 25th Congressional District, Auburn, N.Y., Nov. 1, 1850. Warns of the treachery of professed Whigs attempting to defeat Edwin B. Morgan. (3 cop.) (Mapcase-folder 39)
  - Political (Edwin B. Morgan vs. Locofocos). Cortland County Whig Extra, Homer, N.Y., Saturday, Nov. 2, 1850. Ashbel Patterson, the MUM Candidate of the Locofocos for the Assembly! His refusal to make known his position in relation to the election of U.S. Senator, the Fugitive Slave Law, etc. (Mapcase-folder 39)
  - Political (Edwin B. Morgan vs. Locofocos). Ho, Farmers, Ho! I am persecuted beyond endurance by the d--d Locofocos, etc. Aurora, N.Y., Nov. 1850. Signed, Colonel. An anti-Morgan broadside circulated by the Locofocos. (Mapcase-folder 39)